All right, welcome back to One Bills
Live. Chris Brown, Steve Casker, joining
us in studio, the guy that was pulling
all the cards last weekend. It's Brandon
Bean, general manager of the Bills, who
now has a 10player draft class uh on
board. Second straight year, six
defensive players. Your first five picks
last year on defense, six of the first
eight, I believe, this year on defense.
And you said it after the draft, you
felt this team needed an infusion of
youth on that side of the ball. Team
speed as well. That got accomplished.
We'll get to that in a second. Um
because the 40 times look awfully good
over there on that side of the ball. But
I think it's a fact that maybe a lot of
people didn't recognize, Brandon, that
this roster on the defensive side of the
ball in some spots got old kind of fast.
and rosters, as you said in your press
conference after the draft was over, you
got to transition and make sure you have
enough, not only just regular depth, but
quality depth to turn to, even if it's a
little inexperienced.
>> Yeah, no doubt. It's uh when we went
into this offense, if you look, there's
a a lot more continuity
on offense of of guys that are coming
back that, you know, are are going to be
here and that, you know, that's that's
just where it's at. on defense. Not only
are we transitioning to a 34, which
naturally, you know, how will this guy
fit now? How will that guy fit? Um, you
know, I just think where we are, uh, as
as you mentioned with some of the guys,
whether their contracts were expiring,
aging at the position, whatever that we
needed to get, uh, need to get younger
and faster in as many areas as as we
could. And and I thought we addressed
some of those things this weekend.
One of the things we've been talking
about is that, you know, certainly your
job is to, you know, set the 53 man or
set the 90man roster so your coaches
have stuff they can pick at that they
that they can win games with. How
different was the draft philosophy and
the kind of players you got this year
from years past with MC with Shawn? I
mean, was there a massive difference
like particularly on the defensive side
of the ball about the kind of players
you take or maybe even the specific
players you would have taken in years
past in regard to this year?
>> Yeah, I wouldn't say anything major. I
would say um we did talk about like, you
know, beyond like the position
specifics, you know, of, you know, these
three four, what do you want in the
fore? What do you want in the nose? What
do you want and all that? How do you
want your corners to play? I would say
um there were some players available,
you know, that fit like, you know, our
safeties, you know, can be a little bit
different. They don't have to be exactly
the same way that that, you know, that
we hadn't think about that that we had
him before.
>> Um I think, you know, Jim will do some
different things on the perimeter as
well. And you know, you you take a guy
like Igbonosen who's his number one his
fast ball is is his ability to get up
and get in your face and and press you
and and you got that and then just what
do we need on this team? What do we do
we need some more on this defense? What
do we need? Do we need some more edge?
Uh do we need leadership here? Um, what
do what are the So, we did talk about
some of those things and and part of
that is what are you losing with this
transition that Chris mentioned earlier
of of some of these other players and
then what are we missing? What are we
losing and what do we need to add beyond
just the skill set? So, that's that's
probably a you know a good way to
explain that,
>> right? uh the move back on night one or
I should say the series of moves back.
You explained why you did it in steps
kind of like rungs down a ladder because
you wanted to see how the draft was
unfolding there at the end not miss out
on a run perhaps in the end you move
back nine spots and you're very happy
with what's sitting there. Is that is it
fair for us to assume that you had a
cluster of players in that area? I mean,
cuz you're t I mean, to feel comfortable
to move back nine spots, your cluster
has to be about 12 to 15, doesn't it?
Like, where where was that number at?
>> Yeah. I mean, your cluster doesn't have
to be 12 to 15. It has to be at a
minimum nine. Um, but I would say, and
that's if it falls as worse as it could
ever fall for you, you know. Uh what I
would say is we felt that there were
enough guys and again we had some
opportunities Chris to go from 26 all
the way into about where we ended up
like in one move in one shot
>> in one shot and and you know one one
very beyond fair offer to do.
>> Um but once I got Houston and I told
Houston that and let them know I've got
a really good offer here to go on. Um,
you know, I think Nick really wanted the
pick and and really, you know, we talked
about what it would take and he was
willing to to do that and and that then
at that point I'm able to tell, you
know, the people that Gain has talking
to or Terrence Gray, hey, um, you know,
get back on the phone and tell them
we're moving to 28. Um, and I had, there
was one person I had been talking to. I
got, hey, it doesn't mean we won't move
28. Let's let's get back on the clock.
if your guys still there, let us know
right away and if you want. So that move
probably took us the longest because it
was back and forth. There were some
teams talking about it. One didn't want
to meet where I said it needed to meet,
but New England did and we thought there
was going to be a lot of value in the
middle middle rounds of this draft. And
once they were willing to to part with a
fourthrounder, we at that point we said
we'll go ahead and move back three more
and let's see what's there. and and
ultimately went back to 35.
>> Tell me this, after you traded with New
England, did you have to spit because
there was a bad
>> Some of the fans were ready to do it.
>> Yeah. You know, at the end of the day,
um it's you got to do what's best for
your club in in those moments. And
>> we just felt like we needed to add value
and take advantage of of the depths of
this draft. And and um that's that's
going to rain king all the time. you're
not dying to trade in division, but at
the same time, uh, if the move makes
sense for your club, then you you you
don't hesitate. what pick was there one
of these guys and maybe you've been
asked this already but uh cuz we we were
kind of
kind of happy with the value of it
getting 10 picks and moving up the way
you did and got was there a pick that
you were what was the most surprising
guy that was there when you when you
drafted whether it was your you know
seventh whether it was the punter or
whether it was Igbonos or what what
player on this draft list of 10 guys was
like oh man we got him you know that
kind of guy that you didn't think was
going to be there at that point.
>> Yeah, I mean I would say uh probably
Bell and Kilgore were probably the two
>> that um you know we had pretty good
pretty good grades on our board at least
how we viewed them
>> and um doesn't mean we got them right.
Time will tell if we did or you know not
saying someone else got them wrong by
passing on them. Uh but you know how we
had our board stacked um those were very
easy selections you know when we're back
on the clock
>> I saw that as soon as Skyler gets
drafted you know the network people are
like slot receiver and whatever and I'm
sitting there going what like
>> like a guy with a 41inch vertical isn't
just going to stay inside the whole time
not to mention the fact that he runs a
44 flat so
>> and fortunately you know I saw Joe in
the hallway I was like you just They're
calling him a slide. He goes, "Oh, no.
They asked him to do a lot of stuff at
Yukon. He's going to be more than that."
And I was like, "Okay, good." Like,
that's really good to hear. So, I mean,
just maybe explain
why Bell, even though he's barely six
foot, is going to be able to do a lot
more than just be a slot receiver for
this offense.
>> Yeah, I think that's one of the, you
know, the the pieces that he's valuable
is that, you know, he's he's had plenty
of production on the outside and the
inside. I think that's part of what he
in our system, we would call him a
number four. um you got the versatility
mentally and physically to to move
around and play and play all the spots.
And so that that would be the plan for
him. He's you can watch him um you can
see all that stuff if you just go watch
the Syracuse game alone and and how many
times threw it to him they target him.
But like he's getting back shoulders
outside. He's playing from the slide.
There's plenty of film of him winning
and and doing both and and I think it's
pretty like when we drafted Khalil
Shakir uh we said the same thing. We
said um he can but we we we said Khil is
like inside but can play outside. I
would say Skyler it's like 50/50. You
could you can you know and with Khil
here he's going to be an outside to
inside player. Um, Bell is Yeah, Bell is
My point is I would say we saw Shakir
even more as an inside, but they can
play like I would when the way I
evaluated him is it's true 50/50 whether
you want him on the, you know, whether
he's best on the inside or outside.
>> What did Jimmy Leonard I say Jimmy
Leonard because all the Wisconsin people
are telling us to call him Jimmy. Yeah.
>> All right. So, what Jim Leonard say
about the guys you picked for him on the
defensive side? Got to be he it had to
go across his desk. I mean, he had to be
have at least a a chime in voice.
>> Yeah, no doubt.
>> If not a major voice.
>> No, we I mean, I think um you know,
there was there was a very good
alignment. Joe and I obviously went
through with with Pete, a lot of the
offensive guys and then um No, I sat
down with with Jim and and grabbed Joe
one time and at one point we went
through a bunch of rushers with him and
and his his defensive staff just sitting
in there and talking about, you know,
the various skill sets. slight, you
know, with rushers as kind of like
receivers, what what do they do best? Do
they play the run best? Do they is it
their get off? Is it their their twitch?
Is it their length? Like, and so we kind
of compared these guys like you compare
receivers, right? And from size, speed,
you know, hands, you know, all that
stuff, deep threat, slot only.
>> And we went through all that. And it was
it was good conversation. It was good
for me to hear what they're seeing, what
they're looking for in this defense,
what they need a a Sam backer to do or a
rush backer to do. And then me to also
be able to explain some of these guys
came from college, you know, what what's
the value? What what pays in this
league? What what are teams going to pay
for when these guys hit free agency? And
and just talking about where where the
value meets the skill set. And so, no,
Jim was to answer your question, you
know, Jim was very involved. Jim did a
great job of he really, you know, a lot
of times when these players come in on
the 30 visits, it's uh it's the position
coach will take him out to dinner and
and maybe it's just because Jim's family
is still back in Wisconsin right now,
but uh and he wanted a free meal. I
don't know. But Jim was at a lot of the
Jim was at a lot of the dinners, but he
was he was engaged. he was really coming
back and talking about the guy's uh
personality or his learns or you know
and and the funny thing is with it's
been cool with these college guys Jay
Valai and Terrence Jameson and and Bobby
April and him and all these guys that
came from there because a lot of them
have been on their team Skyler Bell was
at Wisconsin um and you know there's
guys that they coached against they
recruited and so we were able to ask
questions about players on on all sides
of the ball, you know, or if they faced
them, if they've been on their team,
whatever it was. So, it was it was a
cool process, you know, this spring with
this with this new staff.
>> Yeah. Skyler even said he was running
scout team against Jim's defense because
he was a freshman. He wasn't on the
first team offense. He was running scout
team against him every day in practice.
>> Uh I mentioned the speed on defense in
particular. 445 for IGB. Uh 447 for
Elzor, who's both parent, both of his
parents were track athletes in college.
uh 44 flat for Kilgore, 4-32 for Torio.
Um and then on on the edge, I think
there was this perception that you might
add a pure speed edge rusher, but in the
end, it's hard not to notice. All four
of your guys are kind of speed to power
guys, Greg, Bradley, um TJ, and then
Javon.
Is this uh is this also leaning towards
maybe what Jim believes works up there?
because it's hard not to think, okay, he
played in Baltimore, he played in with
the Jets, and those guys had power
rushers, you know, Terrell Suggs kind of
players, Calvin Pace, you know, those
kinds of guys. And it's hard not to
notice some of what you have assembled
here is is similar in nature. Why do you
feel like, or maybe Jim agrees with you,
that power rushers are the way to go
maybe with the advent of the run game
more now? Like what's the impetus there
if there is any?
>> Yeah, I mean, listen, um I would we
could sit here for hours and talk about
this. Um, you know, to get to third
down, you got to stop the run, right?
So, you got to start there. Um, but we
were not adverse. There were some guys
that were quote unquote DPRs, get off. I
mean, some of them went near us and and
explosion, not as good in the run game,
you know, more, you know, more third
down DPRish than than three down. Um,
you just it's it's where you value, but
we wouldn't we weren't against those
guys. it just um but at the end of the
day to me I think if you watch TJ uh a
year ago we did a two-year study on a
lot of these guys and in his two-year
study he just he was able to get more
sack production the year before some of
that circumstances uh or you know and
such may be but I think you saw enough
athleticism and and you know to to get
double digits he didn't have it this
year but yeah there's some guys that
have some some unbelievable get offs and
and the tens. But I think when you look
at TJ's numbers athletically, he still
measures up pretty good with with a lot
of those guys, especially when you
consider the size he's doing it at.
>> Yeah, Brandon, thanks man very much. I
know we're out of time, but appreciate
you stopping in because we know you're
busy and have fun watching these guys
when you get them out on the grass. It's
going to be a lot of fun.
>> Always good to get get some new toys in
next week. SGM Brandon Bean joining